today we're supposed to do the third of
the seven Diamond like Visions what
would that
involve so yeah
Ghana uh meaning s okay meaning the
jewel s Jewel okay s
Jewel and as you know that mostly
involves people have seen emptiness
directly okay and in this particular
presentation the the state of mind
uh certain qualities of the Mind of a
person who has seen emptiness directly
are considered the S
Jewel and then maybe all the people have
seen emptiness are considered the
nominal s Jewel so the real s jewel is
their state of mind and their their
attainments and then the nominal s jeel
is is the people who have uh seen
emptiness directly and then we had
another presentation from the abis saman
car in the second course I I think it is
that said the real sa was people have
seen emptiness directly and the nominal
sa is people wear RS okay I think so now
you're seeing a deeper presentation
we're just going deeper and deeper
that's the idea of an in-depth course
right um and I started out making the
reading like uh 24 hours ago and uh and
I went through it and I said uh you know
there's eight qualities that they have
and very similar to the Buddha Jewel and
the Dharma Jewel that we went through
and the eight qualities weren't
explained very well anywhere and even GJ
doesn't explain them much so I kind of
got tired of trying to squeeze a reading
out of that and
uh there's another famous really famous
uh quotation that we did all the time in
the monastery about the Jewel of the sa
from utara Tantra from this text it
comes pretty much further down in the
first chapter so but it is um talking
about the S jeel and to me it's one of
the most exciting quotations in the
whole Tantra and there's a big reading
you could design around that because
everybody since then has debated this
quotation everybody like so we'll get uh
from 350 ad up to about 1700s or 1800s
we'll get a whole string of debates so I
thought what you might find fun was what
I mentioned previously this that um
sometimes it's really used to just
useful to just follow the debates back
into history you know uh in the
monasteries the monastic textbooks so
like the big three monasteries it's
called denum say
denum denum Dum Dena means like uh it's
ASA meaning seed of Higher Learning uh
and uh Su means the three biggies and
that's uh Sarah ganden and
de um and their textbook writers in the
last 500 years have have struggled with
this quotation that I'm going to write
for you from the UTI Tantra and I
thought it would just be fun to see how
they struggled through the centuries so
I think I have about 10 different
textbook writers in the reading and um
you know all the great ones from all the
great monasteries and then I I thought
I'd write the whole quotation up here
first because it's so famous and I urge
you to memorize it okay it's on your
homework it's on your quiz okay
uh let's see here it disappeared
yeah and what's what's kind of
interesting to me is I memorized it a
certain way in the debate ground and
then when I was searching for it in the
database I couldn't find it in C
textbooks you know and then I I started
to look for pieces of it and then I
realized that over the centuries the
quotation has evolved you know and this
you know from like even holy Lama Ken r
or you know he'll be in a class he'll
have a quotation that in the back of his
mind that he didn't debate for 47 years
you know and then he'll look through
like 14 scriptures and they say oh
forget it it's something like this you
know and then somebody writes that down
in his book and then other people copy
it out of Ken R's book and then it
becomes mushed around so you'll see it
in the reading uh this quotation has
been uh inverted in different ways you
know which makes me uh want to say that
you guys have to be careful okay as you
record these teachings like uh John
stillo wrote me an email he said I
that's cool that you guys are doing
in-depth suture courses in Arizona who's
going to who's going to what do you call
it
uh do you say archive them yeah who's
going to Archive them you know I mean
let's get that straight you know because
we still have a thousand tapes in godo
that we haven't archived yet you know
and so uh he was very concerned that
who's going to be doing the archiving
know and who's going to be sending out
those courses and who's going to make
sure that the content is still is not uh
the quotations aren't all messed up in
300 years you see what I mean so you'll
see in the readings how the quotation
evolved uh over the 300 years you know
and um it's very or sorry over 1600
Years anyway here it is
oh for
and ell I finished the homework about 3
minutes
ago and I don't know if there's any way
you could print it out by or afterwards
since people are all staying for the uh
stuffing party is there a stuffing
party thank you
okay for
and there's a beautiful uh Sanskrit
equivalent and you'll have it in your
next Sanskrit class which is early
August I
guess okay and it's really beautiful if
you get a chance you should do the
Sanskrit of this verse especially
ready not quite but
anyway uh p means wion H yeah oh yes but
P by Aras by Aras okay Aras iron
sansen AR uh
chiwa number four in the prison
yesterday yeah you might notice some
other ones here and
na K we had it
yesterday no sickness okay sickness
you've had n in the last homework n
which means sickness also so you put a
DA on it it means sickness also okay uh
death sickness and dang
gawa old age aging okay there's this big
debate in the moner if you stay old age
you get in trouble oh so babies don't
have GA so babies don't have the
suffering of aging and then get this big
thing
suffering say name means
it's the same
thing uh from the root say means from
the
root bang means they have eliminated it
eliminated got rid of it why didn't he
say saan
Christie uh he's trying to R yeah he
blow his rhyme he blow his meter he'd
have an extra beat in there okay hear it
pap
it would ruin the meter you know so he
threw in which is pretty rare but it
means the same thing it's mul from the
root okay mul anyway uh so what this is
saying is that anybody who has seen
emptiness
directly anybody who has seen emptiness
directly has
eliminated
death uh the the sufferings of death
illness and old age okay has
eliminated so here we
go
yeah okay take a person who just
achieved the first part of the path of
seeing they're in the direct perception
of emptiness called the uninterrupted
level right uninterrupted
pathwa death sickness and old
age so they've gotten rid of it right
yes so two M so they're not going to die
right um not
necessarily
so so they haven't eliminated it from
its root they've just
eliminated they just some cases they've
eliminated pour the poison on the root
than the least take a while to die
oh so you my B so they haven't
eliminated death then then it's still
going to
die
so even though this is gu to
[Music]
right so even though they've eliminated
death from its root they haven't
eliminated death
right
um not immediately but
eventually huh they have yeah duh
duh I don't know we'll
see okay it's a very big debate it's a
huge debate
okay okay anyway we're going
[Applause]
on those are the four sufferings right
we had them in the prison yesterday K
say
k kach k you know people pick on me for
many things but but but one of the
things they one of the smaller things
they pick on me is uh why do you keep
bringing out this death thing you know I
mean Buddhism is just to learn to be
relaxed Buddhism is learn to meditate
Buddhism is learn to watch your breath
you know Buddhism is learn to be
friendly you know Buddhism is blah blah
blah and I keep saying no no the whole
thing is about dying the whole thing is
about changing your body into an angel's
body you know the whole thing is that
and here's another verse to support me
now it's just the accident that it came
up but
but you know that's what Buddhism is all
about I just can't stand all the other
ones I mean in certain places on certain
occasions two certain groups maybe you
would talk about getting C but I was
sitting in the prison yesterday and
there's 30 like hardcore cons were in
the highsec max security one and they're
staring at me and I got to say something
funny fast and and interesting you know
and and I know they're uptight all the
time and I know they want to hear about
meditation but I just went straight to
to death you know I just can't do
anything else I think deep downside
everyone's interested in that actually
you know being calm you'll get calm if
you take care of your death right I
think so so uh and they and they
responded to that I think they really
responded to that because they knew
you're just cutting through the BS you
know you go straight to what matters
okay so Kachi birth rebirth aging
illness and death but there's a problem
here so far what's
that something missing yeah what's
missing he didn't mention rebber okay
but it's only half the verse so give him
a
[Applause]
chance I'm do
this I think everybody in the country
should send a bill to Bill Gates for the
time they waste on trying to get Windows
to work and then all the money could be
redistributed from where it came from
originally uh but
anyway uh
spe
for for
[Music]
say
okay two big problems in life what are
they Karma and mental afflictions Karma
and bad emotions bad thoughts okay lat
on your wangi means by the power of
Karma and mental afflictions
get that's how people get get born
that's why people are reborn
okay you say that one more time yeah
wangi means through the power of Karma
and mental
afflictions people are born by I'm going
to read you the whole verse in English
because it's on your homework I mean
yeah so I'll give you the translation in
a minute okay
um de they may don't have it and so they
don't have
it okay they don't have it and so they
don't have it de May Che May
okay meaning what who wants to take a
shot they don't have it so they don't
have
it who
day yeah a don't have uh Karma and
mental afflictions so they don't have G
birth okay so they don't have
birth let me give you the translation
first
okay CU this is going to take us on to
another
subject you know this is just a
translation thing I like to avoid the
word Arya in most translations because
of the connotations with Hitler and all
that so and the new Aran things and all
that uh although it has nothing to do
with ARA right but so I call them
realized beings as opposed to
enlightened beings they've realized
emptiness but they're not enlightened
yet okay uh so it says realized beings
have eliminated death that's the first
line the second line
reads and sickness and aging from the
root birth comes by the power of
Deeds next line and mental afflictions
Dash
last line they have none and so have
none I got some at the bottom of my bag
oh I got
okay back to our debate
he so I guess um
are yes people seeing emptiness directly
don't have birth
right because the great kind benevolent
llamas of our lineage have constantly
repeated the fact that they don't have
it cuz they don't have them
yeah how could anybody can contradict
Holy Scripture wonderful magnificent
Holy Scripture like you do that's how um
Sarah May says that that's how Sarah May
says that uh when you contradict a
scripture and then every different densa
each different major Monastery has their
own way so ganden will
go you know so when we debate then we go
oh
Pig you know and then they go oh Pig
[Laughter]
huh my said that it just said not what
it says well show me when it says
something else says it says they don't
have it because they don't have them yes
the suffering of birth oh birth and the
suffering birth are
different so you can have to take a
rebirth and not suffer
so so don't have the truth
suffering Aras aren't the truth of
suffering not to huh not to so they
don't have the truth of suffering so
they don't have impurities that are
related to Karma and
claes still so they have the truth of
suffering they are the truth of
suffering they still are the truth of
suffering can you be the truth of
suffering and not be Sam
are AR in
Sam so they're in some but they're not
suffering by the way I'm not just
picking on you this is the whole Crux of
the whole thousand years of debate and
it's just exactly what just came up you
know it's like are they suffering or
aren't they do they have are they the
truth of suffering or not much less do
they have the truth of suffering do they
take rebirth or not what makes them take
rebirth
okay and now I I'll tell you a a verse
the next verse from
mraa says
J um because they have
seen the way things are so well okay
meaning emptiness
right they are Beyond birth and all
those other problems but
okay but still
they
pretend or they just show inbet St right
they just
pretend because they are the the
embodiment of
compassion to take birth to die to get
old and to get sick
sound good so bodh satas only take birth
out of we call NL okay you should know
that
NL n there's a new mlam here right so
it's very famous just out of compassion
karuna and
mam uh their prayers you know may I take
birth in some crappy place to take care
of people there you know only because of
those do AR take rebirth right Michael
yes so they don't have mental so they
don't take rebirth through mental
afflictions right b saas no B SAA AR yes
they wouldn't take rebirth through
mental afflictions so everybody who ever
achieves the first body level achieves
the eighth One
automatically no because it's the eighth
one where you lose your last mental
Affliction so somewhere between 1 and 8
you still got to work you know like
usually how many lifetimes seven
typically seven as many as 16 depending
on your
practice I don't know about that but
anyway that's a different book
okay that's about people keep their tant
BS or not that's another subject okay
that's a very beautiful thing about 16
lives if you keep your vows okay but I
want to introduce you to the idea
of and the reading is really nice and
I'll try to work on it on the planes and
stuff and email it after my vacation to
uh al la or somebody
say l l
Dumba Len dum I've often mentioned a
cumbaa like in The Diamond Cutter Class
A person who has seen emptiness
typically might they they they might
very typically perceive directly that
they have seven lifetimes to go to
achieve
enlightenment seven lifetimes as a human
in the desire room okay so this is one
kind of stream mentor and I thought
um I mean you can experience these
things yourself directly it's like uh um
we were trying to do a lot of Channel
practices during the three-year Retreat
and what we found out is that you can
get three years of Channel practices in
half an hour from somebody you see what
I mean cuz the story is all sitting and
working on it I mean describing it to
you can take a week or something you
know you can go study it with some llama
for about a week and you can get the
entire transmission of Jetson cus
presentations on the channels and
Chuckers or something like that but then
to really do it takes like three years
of just daily all day practice basically
uh C and is almost the same idea you
know I've often mentioned it to you in
terms of of a of a direct experience of
emptiness like if you see emptiness
directly you will in the following hours
after that directly perceive that you
will become enlightened within seven
lifetimes okay at least at most sorry
okay and but I thought you might like to
see the scriptural backup for that if
anybody ever asked you you know like
it's also helpful to
have you know books you can pull out and
say well this is where it talks about
that about the seven lifetimes thing so
it's possible you could even have it the
experience yourself and then go back
later to the books and find it and then
you know write a reading about it for
somebody like that you know what I mean
so I thought it's very helpful to have
it in writing you know uh you say how
did you learn about the seven lifetime
thing and you say well I heard it in a
class from somebody you know they said
well where's the proof for that in the
scripture you know and then it's useful
I think to be able to go to scriptures
and and say so I'm going to do the
scriptural presentation as opposed to
The Diamond Cutter type of presentation
okay uh and that in itself is a little
interesting how it's evolved over the
years and maybe got a little confused
and since the time that it was first
spoken about uh it's found in Abid
Dharma literature in the Abid Dharma
kosha and other texts and it's used in
the description of G gukas which is what
stream enters meaning people who have uh
just seen emptiness directly okay and
there are many kinds of stream enters uh
someday we can go through that chapter
in the
abidos but this one is called a sea Luma
sea means like C coroa which is do you
know C
Coro yeah Wheel of Life this means lives
lives see in this case means Liv
lives to take still that many lives to
take Len without the denu okay be
careful means times how many
times and then d means
seven and then the PA makes it an E I
like to call him a seven
timer okay seven
timer and it's pretty exciting I mean if
you go reading scriptures that say uh
it's 49 billion years until my tra gets
here which is what Liberation in the
palm of your hands
says uh but then you know that it's
possible to see ESS directly yourself
and then within seven lifetimes of
average lifetime now is like 70 years so
that's 500 years like my tra could
happen in 500 years or less if you
practice Tantra and we're going to see
that we're going to we're going to see
some things from Jess Kaa but um
the SE Duma thing for me is very
exciting because it means uh you will be
the next mraa if you just work hard on
the courses and then your meditation and
then your Zing practices and your
Retreats you know
um I put in the reading the def the
techacal definition of a seven
lifetimer and uh it just basically says
uh they will take seven more lifetimes
in the desire realm in this in the same
type meaning they they will continue to
be humans of high uh they have good
intellect they have good
tonkins lots of people taking care of
them like they have enough money they
have enough food they everything is easy
for them and they meet continually meet
great teachers even from the time
they're very young uh Rick jeni pangar
gipa pangar gipa means a stream entor
who abandons all their negativity in in
a gradual
way uh g means a stream
Mentor is the definition of a seven Tim
okay it's not very
complicated basically they're just going
to come back seven more
times or less if they practice
Tantra uh which
[Music]
mean I'm going to I'm going to read you
now I'm just going to start the debate
text okay I'm just going to go through
some debates with
you and uh I haven't translated them yet
so we'll just go as we
go that's
okay and so you just listen you won't
have a reading so you just have to
listen to the debates carefully okay and
then probably later you have to compare
notes with each
other you can get the reading I think in
about 3 weeks maybe okay it's finished
in toban but it's not finished in
English
uh and we'll just go the usual
way and just listen this is from uh I
put the best uh monastic textbook first
so it's
from s k
demad uh I think 1493 1568 but I have it
in the reading so don't worry about it
someone can be the truth of
suffering and not possess the demon of
the heaps okay the demon of heaps there
are four demons in Buddhism that you
destroy as you become enlightened uh the
demon of the heaps means the body and
mind that you are forced to take on when
you came into this life dirty
mortal Troublesome body and mind okay
then there's the demon of the mental
afflictions which doesn't need any
explanation for anyone who's done any
lay rooms or anything uh
or who keeps a book then there's the
demon of death death
itself and then there's a demon called
this the child of the deity named gav
wangu and that just means it's a fancy
way of saying that in the old days when
you were getting close to getting
enlightened uh somebody would show up
and try to take you off track you know
like just before the end or as you get
more advanced you'll bump into some new
friend who and that's some kind of a
demon influence who will try to convince
you that what you're doing is not very
meaningful or they'll try to get you
sidetracked and that's just a common
thing when you're getting towards the
end they'll try to put doubts in your
mind uh the more powerful the more
beautiful the more fantastic things are
happening the more the uh P wangu gets
into action and tries to plant doubts of
plant problems get people distracted
from the real issues like that
okay like if you spent three a thousand
days in a y during
Retreat and then it's you know and you
have the big rejoicing afterwards but
then you get distracted by some other
thing then that would be like you know
[Music]
okay so he says you can have the
suffering of I'm sorry the truth of
suffering you can be the truth of
suffering and not possess the demon of
the
heaps you can be the truth of suffering
and not possess the demon of the heaps
okay can you be a person and be the
truth of
suffering is the truth of suffering and
unchanging things fact right what truth
of suffering fact you
you tell me something is a
fact I think I got here last class and
said
f it's a fact in the sense of the things
which are that that thing it's not a
truth as like a statement or a you see
what I mean it's the reality of those
things so can a person be the truth of
suffering yeah all senion all suffering
sensient beings are the truth of
suffering it's not like they have the
truth of suffering or they believe in
the truth of suffering or they haven't
recognized the truth of suffering they
are the truth of suffering
okay but can you be the truth of
suffering and not have the demon of the
heaps and he
says which means
[Music]
[Laughter]
what stream Mentor who's got seven lives
to go
okay what
suffering they are the truth of
suffering but means but
okay they are not the demon of the
heaps they are
the they are the S so what the monastic
textbooks do they are pedagogical they
are debate they are dialectic you know
they never they don't sit there and tell
you now look there's there three kinds
of stream ANS and then the third one he
has the truth of suffering he is the
truth of suffering but he doesn't have
the demon of the heaps because um he's
the D the S Jewel they just say they
just present an argument between two
people and then they go on and then you
have to you have to suck out you have to
withdraw the information from it so now
you learned something which is what you
learned a bunch of
stuff you learned something about SE
Lumas you learned that these seven time
guys are what truth of suffering they
are the truth of suffering they don't
possess the demon of the heaps because
they
are s Jewel so then you can derive this
thing that anybody who gets to be S jeel
doesn't have this the demon of the heaps
right so anybody who's a s jeul doesn't
have a mortal body right
no they do have a mortal body yeah they
do have a mortal body right right so
they have the demon of the the heaps
right no yeah now you get tricky you
know CU now we're starting to get
questions you're starting to get doubts
you know what what are you talking then
what's the demon of the heaps if it's
not a mortal
body body self existence might be might
be the nice thing about the script the
debate books they don't tell youal body
the yeah you can say that but they're
still going to die that body is still
going to or maybe it turns into light at
a certain point maybe okay maybe there's
a difference that way maybe there's some
kind of difference that way you see
maybe they're on the way they're on the
conveyor belt to become a body light so
they don't count as having a the demon
of the heap's body okay maybe that okay
I propose let's
see uh he throws in another comment by
the way and I just chopped them out you
don't get the whole context but for that
you have to debate a lot he says uh by
the way it's also not true that if you
do have the demon of the heaps you'd
want to get rid of
it that it's a
what
it no it's the ha part PR it's not true
that it's
a okay wow
sure you telling me that if you got the
demon of the heaps is infesting you it's
it's not something you want to get rid
of don't say apparently not you can
probably find somebody from another
monter said the opposite why not why do
you think he said that because it
doesn't have to be
suff no we're talking aboutum pumo means
the ones you were forced that were
forced on you when you were born
okay but he
says a human body which is possessed of
the 18 dra which is what spiritual leers
and fortunes from the L Rim come on this
is a precious thing it's a wonderful
thing you know you wouldn't want to for
example commit suicide okay so it's not
something to be eliminated right you in
the form of double double negative right
it's not true that the stre do not want
to get rid of well no it's not true that
even if your being is is in the clutches
of the demon of the heaps that it's
something you'd want to get rid of
necessarily others so you going to buy
that do you buy that it's not something
to get rid of or we l
say again is this a Sutra debate or a
tate we're coming to the Tantra later
we're coming to the T but let's stick to
Sutra so suffering heaps are not
something to be abandoned because
they're the 18 they have the 18 leisures
and fortunes from the beautiful Lan
books that's what he's saying that's
what the author of our textbook just
said
right yeah yeah yeah there's this thing
where you don't get rid of the boat till
you get over the ocean you know then you
must get rid of the bowet okay is a
contradiction inail because the
streamers do not want to get rid of the
team reps because their streamers they
don't possess them in the first place
that's true too okay anyway here we
go
uh Denise says a little bit uh you want
some detail you want to sit here for
hours I don't know yes uh okay and by
the way it's not even true that if
something is the demon of the mental
afflictions it's a mental Affliction he
says just just in case you were
wondering you got an idea we need a
churen right we need a churen we need
that example which proves the
exception I'll say it again he said by
the way that thing about the demon and
mental afflictions something can be the
demon and mental afflictions and not be
a mental
Affliction and not be he throws in an
adjective that he hopes you don't notice
a manifest mental fiction
so it could be
lat yeah could be a latent mental
Affliction but he goes further he says
you could be the in a way you could be
mixed up with mental afflictions and not
be
mental like he's really pushing the
envelope anything cause that's in one
way but
um what would be in mental Affliction
demon but not be
mental work on
that by the way I mean r brought us up
on these I mean we read these we didn't
do the ACI courses you know we only read
these so you know for anybody who was
there for 30 years ago that's it's
easy say s the bch b b yeah so you tell
me bak's not
mental not manifest yeah well a is not
manifest but B is not mental at all
anyway it's
it's an energy it's a potential you see
if you split the whole world into mental
physical and stuff in between where does
it
go it goes in between it goes in the
demon DUIs okay it's it's a power it's a
potential it's an energy it's not mental
it's not cogn cognant
C cognant cognizant it doesn't perceive
anything you see it's just a an event
waiting to happen in a way okay that's a
box so B talks stay in
your Contin mind but they're not they're
not mind they stay in your mind but
they're not the mind so there seeds
without causes and conditions for
likening who I don't know about that
we'll debate that
later then he goes in this long story
about how you don't have to be uh to be
the the son of the de the child of the
de mental Affliction which just means
someone who distracts you you don't have
to be a child of a daddy but you knew
that okay
okay here's another
bit
uh let's talk about a bodh SATA on the
third level can you think of
one are you sign according to scripture
you know by the end of his life
okay did he get rid of the rough form
rough
form of the demon of the heaps
and then he says
because uh he got he destroyed heaps
which are impure and which come from
Karma and
claes we can agreee to that so far right
I think okay he got rid of the demon of
the heaps because he's gotten rid of any
heaps that are a product of Karma and
claas karmas and mental afflictions good
bu it he's being careful smart let's buy
it let's see where it goes from
there
uh you have to agree to my reason that
he has gotten rid of heaps that are
caused by Karma and mental afflictions
because uh
te because ofh who's on the Mahayana
path of seeing in the moments after
seeing emptiness directly okay we call
it uh
being in the meditation and then when
you get up and start walking around like
an hour later then we call numu numu
means at that point when you start to
you're you're already free of all the
problems that that seeing emptiness
directly eliminates so you're in a state
of Liberation in a sense okay
um because Bon saas who have just seen
emptiness directly are and are walking
around in the 24 hours after that right
they have gotten rid of rebirth and
death which are created by Karma and
mental afflictions because the utar
Tantra says and every single debate I
have in here has this same
quotation okay I I wanted you to see how
10 different people in the last 2,000
years 1700 years have used the same
quotation to prove what they want to
prove okay and it's not bad I mean it it
gives us insight into the meaning of the
quotation okay uh and then he just
quotes that line those lines and he says
by the way
moreover um if you're a person who has
just reached the first bodh level
because you just got bodh and you just
directly I say you must have gotten rid
of the are you are you telling me that
they have gotten rid of uh Heats which
are created by K claes are you telling
me that from that quotation
I mean our guy us come up to the other
guy and say are you telling me that the
guy already just agreed to our quotation
so he said do do you think the quotation
proves that we were trying to
prove say yeah okay good okay
uh me well you agreed
right okay anyway
uh let's talk about a person who's on
the path of preparation which happens
just before
what seeing emptiness directly okay path
of preparation they're on the Mahayana
path of preparation and they just
achieved the path of seeing right just
achieved the path of
seeing um are you saying they don't have
uh heaps which are a product of car and
claes whoa
you can't
agree because the guy who was on the
path of
preparation had a body which was created
by kmen
clus and gang right gik means
and because they have the same they are
the same men the bodily
Continuum I mean 10 minutes later he's a
he's an IR so like 10 minutes before
he's got a body that was produced by car
and Claus are you saying that 10 minutes
later he's he has a different body what
you
know then he just leaves you like that
okay and you have to think about it and
that's what they do you know and R would
do that too you know he'd say we say but
what's the punch R and he' say you go
cook it you go think about it you know
uh one nice thing about the the monastic
textbooks is sometimes they'll just
leave you hanging they won't give you
like Americans people in R classes just
get so frustrated you know they want
what's the end what's the end you know
is there a
den no you got to figure it out okay so
there you go you got stuck with that
one
uh but what did you learn from that last
statement he
said they have one and the same bodily
stream
Continuum what do you learn from
that what what might be implication of
that is that certain parts of the path
of preparation happen like within half
an hour of seeing emptiness directly you
know what I mean like jam Cho you know
highest part of the path of preparation
I mean what he's arguing is that come on
they're so close what he's saying what
he's implying is like they're half hour
apart they're 15 minutes apart you
telling me it's a different kind of body
is God now but what you learned from
that argument even if you didn't have
anybody to tell you that is that the
direct perception emptiness happens like
within half an hour of the highest part
of the path of preparation
okay because it's such a big deal that
the bodies are the same in that half
hour okay all right we'll do one more
and take a break
[Applause]
saying truth ofering if something is the
truth of
suffering it must be it must be some s
yeah whoa cook that one if something is
the truth of suffering it must be some
sign we aren't saying that someone who
seen EMP directly has
achiev are sorry are we you saying that
we can't be saying that no we can't
right because what because they haven't
permanently seized all their mental
right right that's a long ways away
that's 490 years away or something right
uh at least you
know well at most maybe but
anyway what do you guys say this is the
kma kma means what one mouth which
always means the other guy the the Dum
the guy who's saying the wrong thing I
mean luckily they identify who's saying
the first thing right so if you're like
this 13-year-old kid in the monastery
you know it's wrong already but you just
got to figure out why he
says the guy the guy who's always wrong
says if something is the truth of
suffering it must be some
Sor any biters
Brian all you have to do is find a a me
so you have to find a example that
doesn't fit that anation appear
to okay an amination appearing to saric
being uh is
it is it truth of suffering no I we need
something which is a truth of suffering
but is not Sam
S appear to that being have to be in Sam
S for
whom yeah
right but who's the truth of suffering
the guy seeing the the emanation is is
the truth of suffering then the Buddha
from the Buddhist point of view the the
emanating Buddha is seeing themselves in
Sams in samsar but they're not the truth
of suffering well then they would have
to be the truth of suffering if that was
correct oh no he said the opposite if
it's the truth of suffering it has to be
some
s which basically if anything is been
screwed up it has to be the truth it has
to be some
Sor from whose side
again well let's go
on let's consider the impure vessel of
the world this world that we live in
okay that's his counter example okay you
gave the example of a dirad emanating as
a normal being he gives the example of
the world we live in the suffering world
we live
in so what what's the guy going to come
back with now the opponent he's going to
say are you telling me it's the truth of
suffering yeah are you telling me it's
not
Sam the our our guy our boy came and
said take the world suffering World
impure
World which means he thinks it's
what truth or suffering but
not wow let's keep
going uh
I guess it's right and the guy says why
did you say
that do it's the truth of suffering okay
I like this one I remember this one I
busted my head on this in
sah
uh because the guy says oh we say it has
to be the truth of suffering because
kundu Samaya I don't know which one
says what is the truth of suffering
either one suffering sensient beings or
the world they live
in okay so the impure world around us
has to be the truth of suffering because
that book said so that ancient Indian
book said so okay then the guy says okay
I'll go along with it this world is
some says
do when you go up what's it mean
no this is the non-sarcastic one when
you go
down you tell me it's not tell me it's
not but when you go
up means
what no it's not suffering no it's not
Sam okay uh how is the uh tone of your
voice indicated in the
scripture like when you do chanting and
they have chanting U notation they're
these beautiful wavy things they look
like waves they
go and they draw this line like that you
know and but there's no line like that
here how do you know his voice is going
up just the context you just have to
figure it out from the context sorry no
no if what he says is true from what you
figure out later he must have gone up
okay
sorry uh my
because it
ain't it's the place where you
Kwa do the karma
CL
okay it ain't Kwa it's the place where
you
cor it's not the cycle it's the place
where you
Circle
okay I don't know let's see where he's
going to go from there by the way you
don't have to buy him right way you have
to question them that's why they write
them as debates and sometimes they'll
wrap it up wrong and see if you can
catch them okay then you have to be
really
careful what's that s seven timer Chen
means let's talk about a seven timer
take a seven timer okay we can do all
this in tibetan when we start the
university and will be debating I'm
thinking English Sanskrit andent will
debate uh different groups of course or
maybe all the same
anyway are you telling me
he's no he
said are you telling me he is Sam right
why if I'm the debat you're the good guy
I'm the bad guy you said to
me you telling me a seven time Sam I
said why did you say that because you
just said that truth of suffering if
it's the truth of suffering Sor said
that the L is the truth of suffering he
is the truth of suffering okay so I'll
go over it again you opponents said that
if something is the truth of suffering
it has to be some
sah so let's take that seven timer are
you telling me he's Sam why' you say
that I didn't say that but he's the
truth of suffering isn't he that's how
far we are right now the guy's got to
say what yes yeah he's the truth of
suffering of course he a truth of
suffering here's a tough
one because he is a sensient being who
is taking birth in the place called
samsara helplessly due to his his or her
karma and
cliches that
okay well I don't know I don't know I
don't know
we got problems here we got
inconsistencies between the texts now
this guy's saying he's got to be he's
got to sorry he has to be the truth is
suffering because he's going to take
more births in Sam SAR due to the powers
of his due to the power of His Karm and
claes okay and this is a good textbook
writer who is this let me just check oh
this is ours okay this is
s
okay now don't forget that he said that
keep that s Jau keep that note in mind
okay he said this guy helplessly takes
helplessly has to take birth through
Caron clous we just heard M saying
what he takes place through what two
things
oh compassion yeah and compassion and
prayer prayer you know may I may I be
born in a in a in a land full of uh like
they call L lumba means um Barbarian
land like America okay um dharmically
then he says uh
D oh then then the other guy breaks down
he says okay okay okay he's
Sor I said I said he had to be right
because he's a truth to suffer he is
I'm made here now he's not
he's which means what samsar being yeah
he's the one who's in
samsar he's the
samsar
samsar okay he's not samsara he's not
samsara so so far what do you got the
world can't be samsar because it's
what it's the place where you
samsar the guy who's in samsar can't be
samsar he's a
Sams so what's samsar
uh his last or here's a very important
thing where they're cycling or what
they're chained
to okay that's nice if you're talking
about where they're cycling or what
they're chained to and that's going to
be useful later okay it's pumo it's your
body and your mind that you took on when
you were born that's where they're
chained
too and where is this all this cycling
taking place in the world the impure
World say you if you're going to be
precise you got to talk about it that
way but none of these is Sam SAR is
it the place the
person okay the thing they're chained to
that none of that is samsar what is
samsar then he doesn't tell you he he
closes it like
that he leaves it he says don't you guys
uh can't you guys distinguish between
subjects and
objects don't you have the Corum correct
Tessy loves that CH she loves Corum what
are Corum three spheres three spheres
meaning the this person who's cycling in
Sam CCL yeah cycling itself yeah and
what it produces and or the place where
they're cycling okay so which one is
some which one is the real
cycle just get it straight get it
straight people think you know they say
oh New York is samsara you know people
say I I have to go on vacation because I
don't like samsara you know people say
that people say I got cancer my cancer
is samsara what is
samsara it's the condition okay
CH means the condition the fact of it is
some okay it's very subtle and you got
to cook it you got to cook it
uh the implication is uh we are not
living in
Sams and it's not that we are
Sam it's that the condition of being
here is
Sam what's the tantic
implication it's a Feeling
no you could change it you could change
it the place ain't Samar you're not
Samar it's the condition of being here
that's
Sam okay it's the condition of having to
be here through mental
afflictions and karma that's Sam but in
and of itself this isn't Samar and
you're not samsar
being the fact that you're still here is
some s that's very Tate okay you got to
cook that like he's wrting he's not
writing a tantric book but he threw that
in okay okay uh I'd like to go on I mean
I'm not really doing the whole ACI
courses with you this way although they
were all based on these scriptures but
you start to get a feel that if you were
in a debate ground and if you debated
this stuff for an hour then you know
this stuff backwards and forwards you
know you go to Tucson teach somebody at
the Muse was it Arts Center or something
like that I hate to call it the YMCA it
sounds cheap but anyway it's pretty but
anyway uh you really know your stuff by
the end you really know your stuff you
really really grasp it you know and
there are modern Scholars who say all
those monastic textbooks they're just oh
they're just silly they're just
splitting hairs you know but really if
you have Kwa if you have virtue core in
you they're like dieses have written
these things you know like you could
spend your whole life looking at these
things and listening to the debate go
back and forth and by the time you're
done like you get everything you get
everything because they've ripped it
apart from every angle you know it's a
very nice way to learn I think uh debate
debate is really nice being the
prisoners really Lov it it also gives
you a chance to be act a little crazy
and still learn something you know so
it's a very useful thing